<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>The blog of Gursimran</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000"/>
 <updated>2018-12-21T23:24:32-08:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Gursimran</name>
   <email>simar.i3r@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Generative models</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/machine_learning/2018/12/21/vae.html"/>
   <updated>2018-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/machine_learning/2018/12/21/vae</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Machine learning algorithms can be classified into two broad categories. Discriminative models learn the conditional probability distribution of labels given the data p(y|x). These models are easy to train, however, they lack the ability to understand the underlying distribution of the data x. Generative models, in contrast, learn the joint probability density p(x,y). The ability to jointly model data $x$ and labels $y$, allows them to generalize better in case of limited and/ or missing data. They can also be used to compute conditional density using the Bayes rule &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p(y\|x)&lt;/script&gt;.  \cite{ng2002discriminative} provides a nice analysis of discriminative vs generative models and the situations in which we prefer one over the other. Additionally, they can also be used to generate new samples $(x,y)$ from the distribution. For instance, generative models are used to generate new hypothetical faces of celebrity, generate more text in a particular handwriting style and new artificial environments to be used in reinforcement learning. Other applications include super-resolution \cite{ledig2016photo}, conversion of sketches to images \cite{chen2018sketchygan}, etc. &lt;a href=&quot;#ruby&quot;&gt;(Flanagan &amp;amp; Matsumoto, 2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Typically, we train generative models by maximizing the likelihood of the training data &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\theta^* = arg \max_{\theta} \sum_{i=1}^{N} log(p_{model}(x_i;\theta))&lt;/script&gt;. However, optimizing the maximum likelihood objective often becomes intractable in the general formulation of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{model}&lt;/script&gt;. A wide range of models like Gaussian mixture models, Markov chains, and hidden Markov models makes simplifying conditional independence assumptions to make the objective tractable. However, due to the simplifying assumptions, these models are limited in terms of expressiveness. Hence they are not able to model many data distributions of interest which are often non-linear and highly complex. Deep generative models relax some of these strong assumptions and model the joint density using neural networks as a powerful function approximator. Deep generative models can be further classified as explicit density models and implicit density models based on how we define likelihood, its gradients, and any approximations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Explicit density models define an explicit function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{model}(x;\theta)&lt;/script&gt; to represent the probability density of the data. Explicit models that use approximations for the intractable likelihood allow us to use a large class of powerful models. Instead of optimizing the intractable likelihood directly, these models optimize a lower bound approximation of the objective. VAEs fall in this category. The main disadvantage of these methods is that when we have a weak approximation of the posterior or the prior distribution, optimizing the lower bound does not effectively learn the target distribution. Implicit density models do not model the probability density explicitly. Instead, it just provides a stochastic procedure to generate data. GANs fall under this category. These models are trained by directly sampling from the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{model}&lt;/script&gt; using a game theoretic approach between two networks, the generator and the discriminator. However, finding an equilibrium is hard and it makes them hard to train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;Flanagan, D., &amp;amp; Matsumoto, Y. (2008). &lt;i&gt;The Ruby Programming Language&lt;/i&gt;. O’Reilly Media.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Weekend excursion to Prashar lake</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/2017/07/17/Prashar-Lake.html"/>
   <updated>2017-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/travel/2017/07/17/Prashar Lake</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Prashar is a mystery-lake cloistered inside the lush green mountains towards north of Mandi town in Himachal Pradesh &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandi,_Himachal_Pradesh&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone, who is familiar with the hustle and bustle of Mandi, would find it hard to digest that anything worth visiting would lie as close as 50km from it. However the steep accent will take you from 850m to 2730m above sea level. Moreover, the narrow single-lane and tortuous road, with landslides and streams flowing through it, will surely send chills down your spine. Nevertheless, it keeps the faint-hearted away, and the destination will reward you with its serenity and quiteness. On top of that, you will be enthralled by the beauty of lush green grass-lands surrounded by awe-inspiring scenery of mountains and forests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the lake, this place is known for a temple (mandir) dedicated to Prashar rishi. The lake has a small and round island kind of thing which mysteriously keeps on changing its location. There is a mythology related to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prashar_Lake&quot;&gt;[read more]&lt;/a&gt;. This place is ideal if you want to relax and need some time away from the city life. You can sit on the side of the lake, visit temple or just stroll around to cherish nature and beautiful landscapes. Just look around and you will find ample me-spots where you can spend time with yourself and introspect about life. There a couple of eating joints to serve your appitite with delicious rajma-chawal, maggi and tea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travelling to Prashar is very convenient from cities like Chandigarh and Delhi. There are plently of luxury Volvo busses which ply till Mandi. You can book HIMSUTA online busses &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hrtchp.com/hrtctickets/&quot;&gt;[here]&lt;/a&gt;. The only bus which goes to Prashar departs at 8:00AM from Mandi and reaches at 11:30AM. The same bus drives back to Mandi and departs at 1:30PM from Prashar and reaches at around 4:00PM. Apart from bus, you can also drive your own car/ bike to Prashar. I, along with my three friends, drove an XUV to Prashar. Only one among us could accumulate the confidence to drive on the precarious and narrow dirt-road. At many places, we had to reverse the car to let pass the vehicle coming from the opposite direction. So drive only if you have good experience in hills. If you are into trekking, you have a couple of options. Trek from Bagi &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.in/maps/place/Bagi,+Himachal+Pradesh/@31.7631913,77.0877937,13.75z/data=!4m13!1m7!3m6!1s0x3904fc27dd41f4dd:0x469d187643e65f51!2sParashar+Lake!3b1!8m2!3d31.7543645!4d77.1011415!3m4!1s0x3904fc7483247637:0xdc87abe42c996103!8m2!3d31.7764373!4d77.0765913&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt; through Prashar forest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.in/maps/place/Parashar+Forest,+D.P.F.+Parashar+Dhar,+Himachal+Pradesh+175005/@31.7631913,77.0877937,13.75z/data=!4m13!1m7!3m6!1s0x3904fc27dd41f4dd:0x469d187643e65f51!2sParashar+Lake!3b1!8m2!3d31.7543645!4d77.1011415!3m4!1s0x3904fc21cab79a23:0xbfc4333d4378e786!8m2!3d31.7669969!4d77.093854&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt; or through Nal forest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.in/maps/place/Nal+Forest,+D.P.F.+Sarkidhar,+Himachal+Pradesh+175121/@31.7631913,77.0877937,13.75z/data=!4m13!1m7!3m6!1s0x3904fc27dd41f4dd:0x469d187643e65f51!2sParashar+Lake!3b1!8m2!3d31.7543645!4d77.1011415!3m4!1s0x3904feee9d9f85af:0x257b31c104cb4095!8m2!3d31.762436!4d77.1312761&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt; from the other side. However, the trail was not very obvious and we lost our way a couple of times. Finally we managed to find a local guy who helped us. So, take a guide along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to stay at Prashar, you have a couple of options. There are two government rest houses - PWD and Forest. Both of these accomodations are very well maintained and can be booked at as cheap as Rs. 200 a day (including food!). However, since there are government facilities, you need to know someone to get these prebooked from Mandi. In the other case, you can stay at the dorms inside the Prashar temple at similar prices but without the luxuries of attached washrooms, hot water, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chatted with a local guy and found another good site nearby known as Shikari Mata. You can probably visit this place as well. However, you will only get a bus till Janjhelli, after which you have to book a private cab. Otherwise, even a visit at Prashar alone is worth your time and pocket: it will impress you with its profound beauty and silence.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
